<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--

 * Scilab ( http://www.scilab.org/ ) - This file is part of Scilab

 * Copyright (C) INRIA - Fabrice Leray

 *


 * Copyright (C) 2012 - 2016 - Scilab Enterprises
 *
 * This file is hereby licensed under the terms of the GNU GPL v2.0,
 * pursuant to article 5.3.4 of the CeCILL v.2.1.
 * This file was originally licensed under the terms of the CeCILL v2.1,
 * and continues to be available under such terms.
 * For more information, see the COPYING file which you should have received
 * along with this program.

 *

 -->

<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:lang="ja" xml:id="object_editor">

    <refnamediv>

        <refname>object_editor </refname>

        <refpurpose>グラフィックオブジェクトエディタの機能に関する説明</refpurpose>

    </refnamediv>

    <refnamediv xml:id="graphic">

        <refname>graphic </refname>

        <refpurpose>グラフィックオブジェクトエディタの機能に関する説明</refpurpose>

    </refnamediv>

    <refnamediv xml:id="menus">

        <refname>menus</refname>

        <refpurpose>グラフィックオブジェクトエディタの機能に関する説明</refpurpose>

    </refnamediv>

    <refsection>

        <title>説明</title>

        <para>Scilab graphics allow the

            user to have interaction with graphics before and after having them

            drawn. Each graphics window and the

            drawing it contains are represented by hierarchical entities. The hierachy

            top level is the Figure. Each Figure defines at least one child of type

            Axes. Each Axes entity contains a set of leaf entities which are the basic

            graphics objects like Polylines, Rectangles, Arcs, Segs,... It can also

            contain a Compound type which are recursive sets of entities.

        </para>

        <para>The main interest of the graphic mode is to make property changes

            easier. This graphics'mode provides a set of high-level graphing

            routines (see <link linkend="set">set</link>, <link linkend="get">get</link>) used to control objects'

            properties such as data, coordinates and scaling, color and appearences

            without requiring to replay the initial graphics commands.

        </para>

        <para>Graphics entities are associated to Scilab variables of type

            <literal>handle</literal>. The handle is a unique identifier which is associated

            to each instance of a created graphical entity. Using this handle, it will

            be possible to reach entities' properties through "set" and "get"

            routines. The handles are also used to manipulate graphics objects, to

            move them, to make copies or delete them.

        </para>

        <para>To complete and use the graphics handle capacity at its maximum, a

            graphic object editor has been created too. It is a set of Tcl/Tk

            interfaces available for each kind of graphics objects (see

            <link linkend="graphics_entities">graphics_entities</link> for more details) that can be enabled for

            each graphic window. To make it work, select the <literal>Edit</literal> menu in

            the graphic window. Seven graphics editing operations are available :

        </para>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Select figure as current: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Let this</para>

                    <para>figure be the current one.</para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Redraw figure: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Redraw the content of the graphics window.</para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Erase figure: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Erase the content of the graphics window. Its action corresponds

                        to <literal>clf</literal> routine.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Copy object: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Using the mouse, it allows the user to select a 2D object (like a

                        curve, a rectangle...) and put it in the clipboard. Thus, by a next

                        call to <literal>Paste object</literal>, the object is copied in the

                        selected current axes.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Paste object: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Allow the user to paste a previous object put into in the

                        clipboard inside the selected current axes.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Move object: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Using the mouse, it allows the user to move a 2D object (like a

                        curve, a rectangle...) inside the selected current axes.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Delete object: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Using the mouse, it allows the user to pick up a 2D object (like a

                        curve, a rectangle...) inside the selected current axes and to delete

                        it instantly.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Figure Properties: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Launch the Tcl/Tk interface for the Figure object applied to the

                        figure handle of the graphics window.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Current Axes Properties: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Launch the Tcl/Tk interface for the Axes object applied to the

                        current axes handle of the graphics window.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Start Entity Picker: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Start an event handler on the graphics window to catch the mouse

                        clicks on graphics objects and launch the corresponding Tcl/Tk

                        interface. The left mouse-click allows object edition and the right

                        click performs a move of the selected object. Note that, for now, this

                        feature is applied to 2D objects only.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Stop Entity Picker: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Stop the action of the Entity Picker by terminating the event

                        handler on the graphics window.

                    </para>

                    <para/>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para>

            Once the graphic interface is enabled (using the <literal>Figure

                Properties

            </literal>

            or <literal>Current Axes Properties</literal> options), two

            main areas appear :

        </para>

        <para/>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>A tree selector: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Placed on the left side of the graphical editor, a hierarchical

                        tree selector specifies which object is currently edited. It can be

                        used to switch from a graphic object to another provided that they are

                        in the same graphic window.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para>

            <inlinemediaobject>

                <imageobject>

                    <imagedata fileref="../images/tree.gif"/>

                </imageobject>

            </inlinemediaobject>

        </para>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>A notebook: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>The second area represents a notebook composed with different

                        properties pages (like <literal>Style</literal>, <literal>Data</literal>,

                        <literal>Clipping</literal>...) depending on the selected graphic object.

                        Using this editor, man can edit more easily the whole properties set

                        of each graphic object (like through the <literal>"set"</literal> and

                        <literal>"get"</literal> commands). Here is an example of the axes' notebook

                        displaying axes properties:

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para>

            <inlinemediaobject>

                <imageobject>

                    <imagedata fileref="../images/notebook.gif"/>

                </imageobject>

            </inlinemediaobject>

        </para>

        <para/>

        <para>Furthermore, you can legend/annotate your figure using sample

            primitives given inside the <literal>Insert</literal> menu in the graphic

            window. Using the mouse and following the instruction in the message

            subwindow, you can add a:

        </para>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Line: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Draw a line between 2 left mouse clicks. The line lives in the

                        axes where the first point was selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Polyline: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Draw a polyline by clicking on the left button to define the line

                        path and right click at last to complete the drawing. The polyline

                        lives in the axes where the first point was selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Arrow: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Draw an arrow between 2 left mouse clicks. The arrow lives in the

                        axes where the first point was selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Double arrow: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Draw a double-sided arrow between 2 left mouse clicks. The double

                        arrow lives in the axes where the first point was selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Text: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Open a dialog box to enter the text, then click on the figure

                        window to place it. The text lives in the axes where the point was

                        selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Rectangle: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Draw a rectangle : 2 left mouse clicks define respectively the

                        upper left corner and the lower-right corner of the rectangle. The

                        rectangle lives in the axes where the first point was selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para/>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>

                <term>Circle: </term>

                <listitem>

                    <para>Draw a circle : 2 left mouse clicks define respectively the upper

                        left corner and the lower-right corner of the bounding-box where the

                        circle lives. The rectangle lives in the axes where the first point

                        was selected.

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

    </refsection>

    <refsection>

        <title>参照o</title>

        <simplelist type="inline">

            <member>

                <link linkend="graphics_entities">graphics_entities</link>

            </member>

            <member>

                <link linkend="set">set</link>

            </member>

            <member>

                <link linkend="get">get</link>

            </member>

            <member>

                <link linkend="clf">clf</link>

            </member>

            <member>

                <link linkend="plot">plot</link>

            </member>

        </simplelist>

    </refsection>

</refentry>

