<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../manrev.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>external</TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scilab Function</TYPE>
  <DATE>April 1993</DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="external"> Scilab Object, external function or routine</SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <DESCRIPTION>
    <P>
    External function or routine for use with specific commands.</P>
    <P>
    An &quot;external&quot; is a function or routine which is used as an argument
    of some high-level primitives (such as <VERB>ode</VERB>, <VERB>optim</VERB>, <VERB>schur</VERB>...).</P>
    <P>
    The calling sequence of the external (function or routine) is imposed by
    the high-level primitive which sets the arguments of the external.</P>
    <P>
    For example the external function <VERB>costfunc</VERB> is an argument of the <VERB>optim</VERB> 
    primitive. Its calling sequence must be: <VERB>[f,g,ind]=costfunc(x,ind)</VERB> and 
    <VERB>optim</VERB> (the high-level optimization primitive) is invoked as follows:</P>
    <VERBATIM>
<![CDATA[
optim(costfunc,...)
   ]]>
    </VERBATIM>
    <P>
    Here <VERB>costfunc</VERB> (the cost function to be minimized by the primitive <VERB>optim</VERB>)
    evaluates <VERB>f=f(x)</VERB> and <VERB>g=</VERB> gradient of <VERB>f</VERB> at <VERB>x</VERB> (<VERB>ind</VERB> is an integer. Its use is precised in the <VERB>optim</VERB> help).</P>
    <P>
    If other values are needed by the external function these variables
    can be defined in its environment. Also, they can be put in a list.
    For example,the external function</P>
    <VERBATIM>
<![CDATA[
[f,g,ind]=costfunc(x,ind,a,b,c) 
   ]]>
    </VERBATIM>
    <P>
    is valid for <VERB>optim</VERB> if the external is <VERB>list(costfunc,a,b,c)</VERB> and
    the call to <VERB>optim</VERB> is then:</P>
    <VERBATIM>
<![CDATA[
optim(list(costfunc,a1,b1,c1),....
   ]]>
    </VERBATIM>
    <P>
    An external can also be a Fortran or C routine : this is convenient to speed up 
    the computations.</P>
    <P>
    The name of the routine is given to the high-level primitive
    as a character string. The calling sequence of the routine 
    is also imposed. Examples are given in the <VERB>routines/default</VERB> directory 
    (see the <VERB>README</VERB> file).</P>
    <P>
    External Fortran or C routines can also be dynamically linked (see <VERB>link</VERB>)</P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>ode</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>optim</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>impl</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>dassl</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>intg</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>schur</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>gschur</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
