<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Scilab ( http://www.scilab.org/ ) - This file is part of Scilab
 * Copyright (C) 2000 - INRIA - Carlos Klimann
 *
 * Copyright (C) 2012 - 2016 - Scilab Enterprises
 *
 * This file is hereby licensed under the terms of the GNU GPL v2.0,
 * pursuant to article 5.3.4 of the CeCILL v.2.1.
 * This file was originally licensed under the terms of the CeCILL v2.1,
 * and continues to be available under such terms.
 * For more information, see the COPYING file which you should have received
 * along with this program.
 *
 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:id="trimmean" xml:lang="en">
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>trimmean</refname>
        <refpurpose>trimmed mean of a vector or a matrix</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <title>Syntax</title>
        <synopsis>m=trimmean(x[,discard [,flag [,verbose]]])</synopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsection>
        <title>Arguments</title>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>x</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>real or complex vector or matrix</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>discard</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Optional real value between 0 and 100 representing the part of
                        the data to discard. It discard is not in the [0,100] range, an
                        error is generated. Default value for discard=50.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>flag</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Optional string or real parameter which controls the behaviour
                        when x is a matrix. Available values for flag are : "all", 1, 2, r
                        or c (default is flag="all"). The two values flag=r and flag=1 are
                        equivalent. The two values flag=c and flag=2 are equivalent.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>verbose</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Optional integer. If set to 1, then enables verbose logging.
                        Default is 0.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>A trimmed mean is calculated by discarding a certain percentage of
            the lowest and the highest scores and then computing the mean of the
            remaining scores. For example, a mean trimmed 50% is computed by
            discarding the lower and higher 25% of the scores and taking the mean of
            the remaining scores.
        </para>
        <para>The median is the mean trimmed 100% and the arithmetic mean is the
            mean trimmed 0%.
        </para>
        <para>A trimmed mean is obviously less susceptible to the effects of
            extreme scores than is the arithmetic mean. It is therefore less
            susceptible to sampling fluctuation than the mean for extremely skewed
            distributions. The efficiency of a statistic is the degree to which the
            statistic is stable from sample to sample. That is, the less subject to
            sampling fluctuation a statistic is, the more efficient it is. The
            efficiency of statistics is measured relative to the efficiency of other
            statistics and is therefore often called the relative efficiency. If
            statistic A has a smaller standard error than statistic B, then statistic
            A is more efficient than statistic B. The relative efficiency of two
            statistics may depend on the distribution involved. For instance, the mean
            is more efficient than the median for normal distributions but not for
            some extremely skewed distributions. The efficiency of a statistic can
            also be thought of as the precision of the estimate: The more efficient
            the statistic, the more precise the statistic is as an estimator of the
            parameter. The trimmed mean is less efficient than the mean for normal
            distributions.
        </para>
        <para>
            For a vector or matrix <literal>x</literal>,
            <literal>t=trimmean(x,discard)</literal> returns in scalar
            <literal>t</literal> the mean of all the entries of <literal>x</literal>,
            after discarding <literal>discard/2</literal> highest values and
            <literal>discard/2</literal> lowest values.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal>t=trimmean(x,discard,'r')</literal> (or, equivalently,
            <literal>t=trimmean(x,discard,1)</literal>) returns in each entry of the
            row vector <literal>t</literal> the trimmed mean of each column of
            <literal>x</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal>t=trimmean(x,discard,'c')</literal> (or, equivalently,
            <literal>t=trimmean(x,discard,2)</literal>) returns in each entry of the
            column vector <literal>t</literal> the trimmed mean of each row of
            <literal>x</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>This function computes the trimmed mean of a vector or matrix
            <literal> x</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
            For a vector or matrix <literal> x</literal>, <literal>
                m=trimmean(x,discard)
            </literal>
            returns in scalar<literal> m</literal>
            the trimmed mean of all the entries of <literal> x</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal> m=trimmean(x,'r') </literal> (or, equivalently, <literal>
                m=trimmean(x,1)
            </literal>
            )returns in each entry of the row vector
            <literal> m</literal> the trimmed mean of each column of <literal>
                x
            </literal>
            .
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal> m=trimmean(x,'c') </literal> (or, equivalently, <literal>
                m=trimmean(x,2)
            </literal>
            )returns in each entry of the column vector
            <literal> m</literal> the trimmed mean of each row of <literal>
                x
            </literal>
            .
        </para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Example with x as vector</title>
        <para>In the following example, one computes the trimmed mean of one data
            vector, with the default discard value equal to 50 and verbose logging.
            The data is made of 9 entries. The algorithms sorts the vector and keeps
            only indices from 3 to 7, skipping indices 1, 2, 8 and 9. The value 4000,
            which is much larger than the others is not taken into account. The
            computed trimmed mean is therefore 50.
        </para>
        <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[
data = [10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, 80, 4000];
computed = trimmean(data,verbose=1);
 ]]></programlisting>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Example with x as matrix</title>
        <para>In the following example, one computes the trimmed mean of one data
            matrix. The chosen discard value is 50. The orientation is "r", which
            means that the data is sorted row by row. For each column of the matrix,
            one computes a trimmed mean. The trimmed mean is the line vector [25 25 25
            25].
        </para>
        <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[
data = [10 10 10 10
        20 20 20 20
        30 30 30 30
        4000 4000 4000 4000];
computed = trimmean(data,50,orien="r");
 ]]></programlisting>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>References</title>
        <para>Luis Angel Garcia-Escudero and Alfonso Gordaliza, Robustness
            Properties of Means and Trimmed Means, JASA, Volume 94, Number 447, Sept
            1999, pp956-969
        </para>
        <para>
            Trimmed Mean, <ulink url="http://davidmlane.com/hyperstat/A11971.html">http://davidmlane.com/hyperstat/A11971.html</ulink>
        </para>
    </refsection>
</refentry>
