<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../manrev.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>pvm_start</TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scilab function</TYPE>
  <DATE>May 1998</DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="pvm_start"> Start the PVM daemon</SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <CALLING_SEQUENCE>
    <CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>[info] = pvm_start([&quot;hostfile&quot;])  </CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>
  </CALLING_SEQUENCE>
  <PARAM>
    <PARAM_INDENT>
      <PARAM_ITEM>
        <PARAM_NAME>hostfile</PARAM_NAME>
        <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
          <SP>: name of the hostfile describing the configuration for each host of the virtual machine.</SP>
        </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
      </PARAM_ITEM>
      <PARAM_ITEM>
        <PARAM_NAME>info</PARAM_NAME>
        <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
          <SP>: integer, status code returned by the routine. Values less than zero indicate an error.</SP>
        </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
      </PARAM_ITEM>
    </PARAM_INDENT>
  </PARAM>
  <DESCRIPTION>
    <P><VERB>pvm_start</VERB>  starts the <VERB>Pvmd3</VERB> daemon process  which
    coordinates  unix hosts in a  virtual machine.  One  pvmd3 must run on
    each host component of the virtual machine. They provide  the
    communication and process 
    control functions  needed by the user's PVM  processes.  The local and
    remote pvmds can also be started from the PVM console program pvm.</P>
    <P>
    The optional parameter is the name of a host file. See pvmd3 for more
    details on the host file format. If no argument is given to
    <VERB>pvm_start</VERB>, but the variable  PVM_ROOT is set, scilab will try to
    load the file $HOME/.pvmd.conf. If this file does not exist, or the
    variable PVM_ROOT is not set, scilab will try to load the default file 
    $SCI/.pvmd.conf. In all other cases, scilab will supposed that PVM
    and scilab are in standard place on your net.</P>
    <P>
    Note that, to be able to start a PVM daemon, scilex must know the
    place to find both scilex and pvmd. Normally, scilex will start a new
    PVM daemon by using rsh. See the help on pvmd3 and pvm for more detail 
    on how to start/stop pvm.</P>
    <P>
    For example:</P>
    <VERBATIM>
<![CDATA[
pvm_start()
 ans  =
 
    0. 
-->pvm_start()
 ans  =
 
  - 28.  
   ]]>
    </VERBATIM>
    <P>
    Error -28 means: pvm_start_pvmd(): Duplicate host</P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>pvmd3</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>pvm_halt</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>pvm_addhosts</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>pvm_config</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
