<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../manrev.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>edit_graph_menus</TITLE>
  <TYPE>Description</TYPE>
  <DATE>2002</DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="edit_graph_menus"> <VERB>edit_graph</VERB> menus description</SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <DESCRIPTION>
    <P>
  The edit_graph editor  supports the following menus: 
  </P>
    <DESCRIPTION_INDENT>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/New: ">
        <SP>This menu erases the currently edited network.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Zoom: ">
        <SP>This menu allows to set the scale factor for the display</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Replot: ">
        <SP>This menu erases and re-displays the network.</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the
    &quot;<VERB>r</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the 
    edition window. 
    </P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Find Node: ">
        <SP>This menu asks for a node number or a node name. If this node
    exists the view is modified such as the node appears in the middle
    of the graphic window.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Find Arc: ">
        <SP>This menu asks for an arc number or aa arc name. If this arc
    exists the view is modified such as the arc appears in the middle
    of the graphic window.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/SaveAs: ">
        <SP>This menu  allows to save the graph under a specified name</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Save: ">
        <SP>This menu  allows to save the graph under its current name</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>s</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window. </P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Load: ">
        <SP>This menu  allows to load a &quot;graph&quot; file.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Options: ">
        <SP>This menu  allows to set global graph properties
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>o</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Settings: ">
        <SP>This menu  allows to set if graph is directed or not. It also sets
    default values for node diameter, node
    border width, edge width, and font size.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Information: ">
        <SP>This menu  outputs  graph informations, like number of nodes,
    number of arcs, nodes properties ans arc properties.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Graph/Quit: ">
        <SP>Use this menu to exit out of the editor.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/NewNode: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;node addition&quot;.  To
    add a node just click on its desired position. This edition mode
    can also be entered pressing the &quot;n&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window (Under windows, the edition window should also have
    the focus). It is the current editing mode when edit_graph is
    started. This mode remains active until an other edition mode
    is selected.</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>n</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window. </P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/NewArc: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;edge addition&quot;. To
    add an edge between two nodes just left click on the initial node and
    on the final node (click on right button cancels current edge
    addition).</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode
    can also be entered pressing the &quot;a&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window (Under windows, the edition window should also have
    the focus). This mode remains active until an other edition mode
    is selected.
    </P>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>a</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window. 
    </P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Move Node: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;move node&quot;. To
    move a node just left click on the selected node move the mouse up
    to the final position and left click  (click on right button
    cancels move).</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>m</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window. 
    </P>
        <P>
    This mode remains active until an other edition mode is selected.</P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Move Region: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;move region mode&quot;. To
    move a rectangular region just click left on a rectangle corner,
    drag rectangle to the desired area, click left to validate the
    area (click on right button cancels move) then move the rectangle
    to the desired position and click to validate.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Copy Region To ClipBoard: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;copy region to
    clipboard mode&quot;. To copy a rectangular region into the edit_graph
    clipboard just click left on a rectangle corner, drag rectangle to
    the desired area, click left to validate the area (click on right
    button cancels copy) .</SP>
        <P>
    The edit_graph clipboard is shared by all edit_graph editors.
    </P>
        <P>
    This mode remains active until an other edition mode is selected.</P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Paste: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;paste from clipboard mode&quot; to
    clipboard mode&quot;. To paste clipboard into the edit_graph editor
     click left to select the editor window, drag rectangle to
    the desired area, click left to validate the position (click on right
    button cancels copy) .</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>v</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window. 
    </P>
        <P>   This mode remains active until an other edition mode is selected.</P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Delete: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;delete object mode&quot;. To
    delete a node or an edge just left click on the selected object.</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the
    &quot;<VERB>d</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the 
    edition window. 
    </P>
        <P>
    This mode remains active until an other edition mode is selected.</P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Delete Region">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;delete region mode&quot;. To
    delete a rectangular region just click left on a rectangle corner,
    drag rectangle to the desired area, click left to validate the
    area (click on right button cancels selection).</SP>
        <P>
    Note that the deleted region is not send to the clipboard</P>
        <P>
    This mode remains active until an other edition mode is selected.
     This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the &quot;<VERB>x</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the
    edition window. </P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Properties: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;set object
     properties&quot;. To set a node or an edge properties, just left click
     on the selected object; a popup dialog appears.</SP>
        <P> This
     mode remains active until an other edition mode is selected.</P>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the
    &quot;<VERB>p</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the 
    edition window.  </P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Default names: ">
        <SP>This menu automatically sets the node and egde names properties to
    node and egde internal number.</SP>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
      <DESCRIPTION_ITEM label="Edit/Undo: ">
        <SP>This menu set the current edition mode to &quot;undo previous
     edition&quot;. It can be used recursively.</SP>
        <P>
    This edition mode  can also be entered pressing the
    &quot;<VERB>u</VERB>&quot; key while locator is in the 
    edition window.</P>
      </DESCRIPTION_ITEM>
    </DESCRIPTION_INDENT>
    <P>
    Note that Under windows, the shortcuts are taken into accound only if
    the edition  have  the focus.</P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>edit_graph</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
