<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?> 
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../man.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>scicos_model  </TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scicos data structure  </TYPE>
  <DATE>Decembre 2002  </DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="scicos_model"> Scicos block functionality  data structure  </SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <ITEMIZE label='DEFINITION'>
  <VERBATIM><![CDATA[
model=mlist(['model','sim','in','out','evtin','evtout','state',..
 'dstate','rpar','ipar','blocktype','firing','dep_ut',..
 'label'],sim,in,out,evtin,evtout,state,dstate,rpar,..
 ipar,blocktype,firing,dep_ut,label)

   ]]></VERBATIM>
  <ITEM label='model: Scilab mlist, Scicos model data structure defined by the'>
formal name &apos;model&apos; and containing the following fields:

  </ITEM>
  </ITEMIZE>
  <ITEMIZE label='FIELDS'>
  <ITEM label='sim'>
: list(fun,typ) or fun. In the latest case typ is supposed to be 0.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='fun'>
: character string, the name of the block simulation function (a  linked C or Fortran procedure  or a Scilab function).

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='typ'>
: integer, calling sequence type of simulation function (see documentation for more precision).

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='in'>
: column vector of integers, input port sizes indexed from top to bottom of the block. If no input port exist <VERB>in==[]</VERB>.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='out'>
: column vector of integers, output port sizes indexed from top to bottom of the block. If no output port exist <VERB>in==[]</VERB>.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='evtin'>
: column vector of ones, the size of <VERB>evtin</VERB> gives the number of event input ports. If no event input port exists <VERB>evtin</VERB> must be equal to <VERB>[]</VERB>.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='evtout'>
: column vector of ones, the size of <VERB>evtout</VERB> gives the number of event output ports. If no event output port exists <VERB>evtout</VERB> must be equal to <VERB>[]</VERB>.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='state'>
: column vector, the initial continuous state of the block. Must be <VERB>[]</VERB> if no continuous state.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='dstate'>
: column vector, the initial discrete state of the block. Must be <VERB>[]</VERB> if no discrete state.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='rpar'>
: column vector, the vector of floating point block parameters. Must be <VERB>[]</VERB> if no floating point parameters.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='ipar'>
: column vector, the vector of integer  block parameters. Must be <VERB>[]</VERB> if no integer parameters.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='blocktype'>
: a character with possible values:

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label=':'>
&apos;c&apos;  block output depend continuously of the time.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label=':'>
&apos;d&apos; block output changes only on input events.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label=':'>
&apos;z&apos; zero crossing block

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label=':'>
&apos;l&apos; logical block

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='firing'>
: a vector whose size is equal to the size of <VERB>evtout</VERB>&gt; It contains output initial event dates (Events generated before any input event arises). Negative values stands for no initial event on the corresponding port.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='dep_ut'>
: 1x 2 vector of boolean <VERB>[dep_u, dep_t]</VERB>, <VERB>dep_u</VERB> must be true if output depends continuously of the input, <VERB>dep_t</VERB> must be true if output depends continuously of the time.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='label'>
: a character string, used as a label 

  </ITEM>
  </ITEMIZE>
  <DESCRIPTION>
  <P>
    Scicos block model data structure contains all information relative
    to the simulation functionalities of the block. Fields may be
    fixed by block definition or set. 
  </P>
  <P>
    If block is a super block, the fields
    <VERB>state</VERB>,<VERB>dstate</VERB>,<VERB>ipar</VERB>,<VERB>blocktype</VERB>,<VERB>firing</VERB>,
    <VERB>dep_ut</VERB>, are unused. 
  </P>
  <P>
    The <VERB>rpar</VERB> field contains a
    data structure similar to the <VERB>scicos_diagram</VERB> data structure.
  </P>
  <P>
  </P>
  <P>
  </P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM> <LINK>scicos_model</LINK> </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>     <SEE_ALSO_ITEM> <LINK>scicos_diagram</LINK> </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
