<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?> 
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../man.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>scifunc_block  </TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scicos Block  </TYPE>
  <DATE>Janvier 1996  </DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="scifunc_block"> Scicos block defined interactively  </SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <DESCRIPTION>
  <P>
    This block can realize any type of Scicos block. The function of the
    block is defined interactively using dialogue boxes and in Scilab
    language. During simulation, these instructions are interpreted by
    Scilab; the simulation of diagrams that include these types of blocks 
    is slower. For more information see Scicos reference manual.
  </P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <ITEMIZE label='DIALOGUE PARAMETERS'>
  <ITEM label='number of inputs'>
: a scalar. Number of regular input ports

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='number of outputs'>
: a scalar. Number of regular output ports

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='number of input events'>
: a scalar. Number of input event ports

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='number of output events'>
: a scalar. Number of output event ports

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Initial continuous state'>
: a column vector.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Initial discrete state'>
: a column vector.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='System type'>
: a string: c or d (CBB or DBB, other types are not supported).

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='System parameter'>
: column vector. Any parameters used in the block can be defined here a column vector.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='initial firing'>
: vector. Size of this vector corresponds to the number of event outputs. The value of the i-th entry specifies the time of the preprogrammed event firing on the i-th output event port. If less than zero, no event is preprogrammed. 

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Instructions'>
: other dialogues are opened consecutively where used may input Scilab code associated with the computations needed (block initialization, outputs, continuous and  discrete state, output events date, block ending), 

  </ITEM>
  </ITEMIZE>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM> <LINK>GENERIC_f</LINK> </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
