<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Scilab ( http://www.scilab.org/ ) - This file is part of Scilab
 * Copyright (C) INRIA -
 *
 * Copyright (C) 2012 - 2016 - Scilab Enterprises
 *
 * This file is hereby licensed under the terms of the GNU GPL v2.0,
 * pursuant to article 5.3.4 of the CeCILL v.2.1.
 * This file was originally licensed under the terms of the CeCILL v2.1,
 * and continues to be available under such terms.
 * For more information, see the COPYING file which you should have received
 * along with this program.
 *
 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:id="getsystemmetrics" xml:lang="en">
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>getsystemmetrics</refname>
        <refpurpose>Retrieves the specified system metric or system configuration
            setting (Windows only)
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <title>Syntax</title>
        <synopsis>res = getsystemmetrics(key)</synopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsection>
        <title>Arguments</title>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>res</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a value (integer)</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>key</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a string (see below)</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>Retrieves the specified system metric or system configuration
            setting.
        </para>
        <informaltable border="1">
            <tr>
                <td>SM_ARRANGE</td>
                <td>The flags that specify how the system arranged minimized windows.
                    For more information, see the Remarks section in this topic.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CLEANBOOT</td>
                <td>The value that specifies how the system is started: 0 Normal boot
                    1 Fail-safe boot 2 Fail-safe with network boot A fail-safe boot (also
                    called SafeBoot, Safe Mode, or Clean Boot) bypasses the user startup
                    files.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CMONITORS</td>
                <td>The number of display monitors on a desktop. For more information,
                    see the Remarks section in this topic.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CMOUSEBUTTONS</td>
                <td>The number of buttons on a mouse, or zero if no mouse is
                    installed.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXBORDER</td>
                <td>The width of a window border, in pixels. This is equivalent to the
                    SM_CXEDGE value for windows with the 3-D look.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXCURSOR</td>
                <td>The width of a cursor, in pixels. The system cannot create cursors
                    of other sizes.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXDLGFRAME</td>
                <td>This value is the same as SM_CXFIXEDFRAME.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXDOUBLECLK</td>
                <td>The width of the rectangle around the location of a first click in
                    a double-click sequence, in pixels. The second click must occur within
                    the rectangle that is defined by SM_CXDOUBLECLK and SM_CYDOUBLECLK for
                    the system to consider the two clicks a double-click. The two clicks
                    must also occur within a specified time. To set the width of the
                    double-click rectangle, call SystemParametersInfo with
                    SPI_SETDOUBLECLKWIDTH.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXDRAG</td>
                <td>The number of pixels on either side of a mouse-down point that the
                    mouse pointer can move before a drag operation begins. This allows the
                    user to click and release the mouse button easily without
                    unintentionally starting a drag operation. If this value is negative,
                    it is subtracted from the left of the mouse-down point and added to
                    the right of it.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXEDGE</td>
                <td>The width of a 3-D border, in pixels. This metric is the 3-D
                    counterpart of SM_CXBORDER.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXFIXEDFRAME</td>
                <td>The thickness of the frame around the perimeter of a window that
                    has a caption but is not sizable, in pixels. SM_CXFIXEDFRAME is the
                    height of the horizontal border, and SM_CYFIXEDFRAME is the width of
                    the vertical border. This value is the same as SM_CXDLGFRAME.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXFOCUSBORDER</td>
                <td>The width of the left and right edges of the focus rectangle that
                    the DrawFocusRect draws. This value is in pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXFRAME</td>
                <td>This value is the same as SM_CXSIZEFRAME.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXFULLSCREEN</td>
                <td>The width of the client area for a full-screen window on the
                    primary display monitor, in pixels. To get the coordinates of the
                    portion of the screen that is not obscured by the system taskbar or by
                    application desktop toolbars, call the SystemParametersInfo function
                    with the SPI_GETWORKAREA value.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXHSCROLL</td>
                <td>The width of the arrow bitmap on a horizontal scroll bar, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXHTHUMB</td>
                <td>The width of the thumb box in a horizontal scroll bar, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXICON</td>
                <td>The default width of an icon, in pixels. The LoadIcon function can
                    load only icons with the dimensions that SM_CXICON and SM_CYICON
                    specifies.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXICONSPACING</td>
                <td>The width of a grid cell for items in large icon view, in pixels.
                    Each item fits into a rectangle of size SM_CXICONSPACING by
                    SM_CYICONSPACING when arranged. This value is always greater than or
                    equal to SM_CXICON.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMAXIMIZED</td>
                <td>The default width, in pixels, of a maximized top-level window on
                    the primary display monitor.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMAXTRACK</td>
                <td>The default maximum width of a window that has a caption and
                    sizing borders, in pixels. This metric refers to the entire desktop.
                    The user cannot drag the window frame to a size larger than these
                    dimensions. A window can override this value by processing the
                    WM_GETMINMAXINFO message.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMENUCHECK</td>
                <td>The width of the default menu check-mark bitmap, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMENUSIZE</td>
                <td>The width of menu bar buttons, such as the child window close
                    button that is used in the multiple document interface, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMIN</td>
                <td>The minimum width of a window, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMINIMIZED</td>
                <td>The width of a minimized window, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMINSPACING</td>
                <td>The width of a grid cell for a minimized window, in pixels. Each
                    minimized window fits into a rectangle this size when arranged. This
                    value is always greater than or equal to SM_CXMINIMIZED.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXMINTRACK</td>
                <td>The minimum tracking width of a window, in pixels. The user cannot
                    drag the window frame to a size smaller than these dimensions. A
                    window can override this value by processing the WM_GETMINMAXINFO
                    message.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXPADDEDBORDER</td>
                <td>The amount of border padding for captioned windows, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXSCREEN</td>
                <td>The width of the screen of the primary display monitor, in pixels.
                    This is the same value obtained by calling GetDeviceCaps as follows:
                    GetDeviceCaps( hdcPrimaryMonitor, HORZRES).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXSIZE</td>
                <td>The width of a button in a window caption or title bar, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXSIZEFRAME</td>
                <td>The thickness of the sizing border around the perimeter of a
                    window that can be resized, in pixels. SM_CXSIZEFRAME is the width of
                    the horizontal border, and SM_CYSIZEFRAME is the height of the
                    vertical border. This value is the same as SM_CXFRAME.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXSMICON</td>
                <td>The recommended width of a small icon, in pixels. Small icons
                    typically appear in window captions and in small icon view.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXSMSIZE</td>
                <td>The width of small caption buttons, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXVIRTUALSCREEN</td>
                <td>The width of the virtual screen, in pixels. The virtual screen is
                    the bounding rectangle of all display monitors. The SM_XVIRTUALSCREEN
                    metric is the coordinates for the left side of the virtual
                    screen.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CXVSCROLL</td>
                <td>The width of a vertical scroll bar, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYBORDER</td>
                <td>The height of a window border, in pixels. This is equivalent to
                    the SM_CYEDGE value for windows with the 3-D look.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYCAPTION</td>
                <td>The height of a caption area, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYCURSOR</td>
                <td>The height of a cursor, in pixels. The system cannot create
                    cursors of other sizes.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYDLGFRAME</td>
                <td>This value is the same as SM_CYFIXEDFRAME.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYDOUBLECLK</td>
                <td>The height of the rectangle around the location of a first click
                    in a double-click sequence, in pixels. The second click must occur
                    within the rectangle defined by SM_CXDOUBLECLK and SM_CYDOUBLECLK for
                    the system to consider the two clicks a double-click. The two clicks
                    must also occur within a specified time. To set the height of the
                    double-click rectangle, call SystemParametersInfo with
                    SPI_SETDOUBLECLKHEIGHT.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYDRAG</td>
                <td>The number of pixels above and below a mouse-down point that the
                    mouse pointer can move before a drag operation begins. This allows the
                    user to click and release the mouse button easily without
                    unintentionally starting a drag operation. If this value is negative,
                    it is subtracted from above the mouse-down point and added below
                    it.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYEDGE</td>
                <td>The height of a 3-D border, in pixels. This is the 3-D counterpart
                    of SM_CYBORDER.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYFIXEDFRAME</td>
                <td>The thickness of the frame around the perimeter of a window that
                    has a caption but is not sizable, in pixels. SM_CXFIXEDFRAME is the
                    height of the horizontal border, and SM_CYFIXEDFRAME is the width of
                    the vertical border. This value is the same as SM_CYDLGFRAME.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYFOCUSBORDER</td>
                <td>The height of the top and bottom edges of the focus rectangle
                    drawn by DrawFocusRect. This value is in pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYFRAME</td>
                <td>This value is the same as SM_CYSIZEFRAME.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYFULLSCREEN</td>
                <td>The height of the client area for a full-screen window on the
                    primary display monitor, in pixels. To get the coordinates of the
                    portion of the screen not obscured by the system taskbar or by
                    application desktop toolbars, call the SystemParametersInfo function
                    with the SPI_GETWORKAREA value.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYHSCROLL</td>
                <td>The height of a horizontal scroll bar, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYICON</td>
                <td>The default height of an icon, in pixels. The LoadIcon function
                    can load only icons with the dimensions SM_CXICON and SM_CYICON.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYICONSPACING</td>
                <td>The height of a grid cell for items in large icon view, in pixels.
                    Each item fits into a rectangle of size SM_CXICONSPACING by
                    SM_CYICONSPACING when arranged. This value is always greater than or
                    equal to SM_CYICON.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYKANJIWINDOW</td>
                <td>For double byte character set versions of the system, this is the
                    height of the Kanji window at the bottom of the screen, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMAXIMIZED</td>
                <td>The default height, in pixels, of a maximized top-level window on
                    the primary display monitor.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMAXTRACK</td>
                <td>The default maximum height of a window that has a caption and
                    sizing borders, in pixels. This metric refers to the entire desktop.
                    The user cannot drag the window frame to a size larger than these
                    dimensions. A window can override this value by processing the
                    WM_GETMINMAXINFO message.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMENU</td>
                <td>The height of a single-line menu bar, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMENUCHECK</td>
                <td>The height of the default menu check-mark bitmap, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMENUSIZE</td>
                <td>The height of menu bar buttons, such as the child window close
                    button that is used in the multiple document interface, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMIN</td>
                <td>The minimum height of a window, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMINIMIZED</td>
                <td>The height of a minimized window, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMINSPACING</td>
                <td>The height of a grid cell for a minimized window, in pixels. Each
                    minimized window fits into a rectangle this size when arranged. This
                    value is always greater than or equal to SM_CYMINIMIZED.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYMINTRACK</td>
                <td>The minimum tracking height of a window, in pixels. The user
                    cannot drag the window frame to a size smaller than these dimensions.
                    A window can override this value by processing the WM_GETMINMAXINFO
                    message.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYSCREEN</td>
                <td>The height of the screen of the primary display monitor, in
                    pixels. This is the same value obtained by calling GetDeviceCaps as
                    follows: GetDeviceCaps( hdcPrimaryMonitor, VERTRES).
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYSIZE</td>
                <td>The height of a button in a window caption or title bar, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYSIZEFRAME</td>
                <td>The thickness of the sizing border around the perimeter of a
                    window that can be resized, in pixels. SM_CXSIZEFRAME is the width of
                    the horizontal border, and SM_CYSIZEFRAME is the height of the
                    vertical border. This value is the same as SM_CYFRAME.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYSMCAPTION</td>
                <td>The height of a small caption, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYSMICON</td>
                <td>The recommended height of a small icon, in pixels. Small icons
                    typically appear in window captions and in small icon view.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYSMSIZE</td>
                <td>The height of small caption buttons, in pixels.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYVIRTUALSCREEN</td>
                <td>The height of the virtual screen, in pixels. The virtual screen is
                    the bounding rectangle of all display monitors. The SM_YVIRTUALSCREEN
                    metric is the coordinates for the top of the virtual screen.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYVSCROLL</td>
                <td>The height of the arrow bitmap on a vertical scroll bar, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_CYVTHUMB</td>
                <td>The height of the thumb box in a vertical scroll bar, in
                    pixels.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_DBCSENABLED</td>
                <td>Nonzero if User32.dll supports DBCS; otherwise, 0.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_DEBUG</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the debug version of User.exe is installed; otherwise,
                    0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_IMMENABLED</td>
                <td>Nonzero if Input Method Manager/Input Method Editor features are
                    enabled; otherwise, 0. SM_IMMENABLED indicates whether the system is
                    ready to use a Unicode-based IME on a Unicode application. To ensure
                    that a language-dependent IME works, check SM_DBCSENABLED and the
                    system ANSI code page. Otherwise the ANSI-to-Unicode conversion may
                    not be performed correctly, or some components like fonts or registry
                    settings may not be present.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_MEDIACENTER</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the current operating system is the Windows XP, Media
                    Center Edition, 0 if not.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_MENUDROPALIGNMENT</td>
                <td>Nonzero if drop-down menus are right-aligned with the
                    corresponding menu-bar item; 0 if the menus are left-aligned.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_MIDEASTENABLED</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the system is enabled for Hebrew and Arabic languages,
                    0 if not.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_MOUSEPRESENT</td>
                <td>Nonzero if a mouse is installed; otherwise, 0. This value is
                    rarely zero, because of support for virtual mice and because some
                    systems detect the presence of the port instead of the presence of a
                    mouse.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_MOUSEHORIZONTALWHEELPRESENT</td>
                <td>Nonzero if a mouse with a horizontal scroll wheel is installed;
                    otherwise 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_MOUSEWHEELPRESENT</td>
                <td>Nonzero if a mouse with a vertical scroll wheel is installed;
                    otherwise 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_NETWORK</td>
                <td>The least significant bit is set if a network is present;
                    otherwise, it is cleared. The other bits are reserved for future
                    use.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_PENWINDOWS</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the Microsoft Windows for Pen computing extensions are
                    installed; zero otherwise.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_REMOTECONTROL</td>
                <td>This system metric is used in a Terminal Services environment. Its
                    value is nonzero if the current session is remotely controlled;
                    otherwise, 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_REMOTESESSION</td>
                <td>This system metric is used in a Terminal Services environment. If
                    the calling process is associated with a Terminal Services client
                    session, the return value is nonzero. If the calling process is
                    associated with the Terminal Server console session, the return value
                    is 0. The console session is not necessarily the physical console. For
                    more information, see WTSGetActiveConsoleSessionId.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SAMEDISPLAYFORMAT</td>
                <td>Nonzero if all the display monitors have the same color format,
                    otherwise, 0. Two displays can have the same bit depth, but different
                    color formats. For example, the red, green, and blue pixels can be
                    encoded with different numbers of bits, or those bits can be located
                    in different places in a pixel color value.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SECURE</td>
                <td>This system metric should be ignored; it always returns 0.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SERVERR2</td>
                <td>The build number if the system is Windows Server 2003 R2;
                    otherwise, 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SHOWSOUNDS</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the user requires an application to present information
                    visually in situations where it would otherwise present the
                    information only in audible form; otherwise, 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SHUTTINGDOWN</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the current session is shutting down; otherwise,
                    0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SLOWMACHINE</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the computer has a low-end (slow) processor; otherwise,
                    0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_STARTER</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the current operating system is Windows XP Starter
                    Edition; otherwise, 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_SWAPBUTTON</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the meanings of the left and right mouse buttons are
                    swapped; otherwise, 0.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_TABLETPC</td>
                <td>Nonzero if the current operating system is the Windows XP Tablet
                    PC edition, 0 if not.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_XVIRTUALSCREEN</td>
                <td>The coordinates for the left side of the virtual screen. The
                    virtual screen is the bounding rectangle of all display monitors. The
                    SM_CXVIRTUALSCREEN metric is the width of the virtual screen.
                </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>SM_YVIRTUALSCREEN</td>
                <td>The coordinates for the top of the virtual screen. The virtual
                    screen is the bounding rectangle of all display monitors. The
                    SM_CYVIRTUALSCREEN metric is the height of the virtual screen.
                </td>
            </tr>
        </informaltable>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Examples</title>
        <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[
getsystemmetrics('SM_MOUSEPRESENT')
getsystemmetrics('SM_SLOWMACHINE')
getsystemmetrics('SM_REMOTESESSION');
 ]]></programlisting>
    </refsection>
</refentry>
