<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../manrev.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>GENERIC_f</TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scicos Block</TYPE>
  <DATE>Janvier 1996</DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="GENERIC_f"> Scicos generic interfacing function</SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <DESCRIPTION>
    <P>
    This block can realize any type of block. The computational function
    must already be defined in Scilab, Fortran or C code.
  </P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <SECTION label="Dialogue parameters">
    <ITEMIZE>
      <ITEM label="simulation function">
        <SP>: a character string, the name of the computational  function</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="function type">
        <SP>: a non negative integer, the type of the computational  function</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="input port sizes">
        <SP>: a vector of integers, size of regular input ports.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="output port sizes">
        <SP>: a vector of integers, size of regular output ports.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="input event port sizes">
        <SP>: a vector of ones, size of event input ports. The size of the vector gives the number of event input ports.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="output event port sizes">
        <SP>: a vector of ones, size of event output ports. The size of the vector gives the number of of event output ports.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="Initial continuous state">
        <SP>: a column vector.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="Initial discrete state">
        <SP>: a column vector.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="System type">
        <SP>: a string: c,d, z or l (CBB, DBB, zero crossing or synchro).</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="Real parameter vector">
        <SP>: column vector. Any parameters used in the block can be defined here as a column vector.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="Integer parameter vector">
        <SP>: column vector. Any integer parameters used in the block can be defined here as a column vector.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="initial firing">
        <SP>: vector. Size of this vector corresponds to the number of event outputs. The value of the i-th entry specifies the time of the preprogrammed event firing on the i-th output event port. If less than zero, no event is preprogrammed.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="direct feedthrough">
        <SP>: character &quot;y&quot; or &quot;n&quot;, specifies if block has a direct input to output feedthrough.</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="Time dependance">
        <SP>: character &quot;y&quot; or &quot;n&quot;, specifies if block output depends explicitly on time.</SP>
      </ITEM>
    </ITEMIZE>
  </SECTION>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
      <LINK>scifunc_block</LINK>
    </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
