<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?> 
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../man.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>SCOPE_f  </TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scicos Block  </TYPE>
  <DATE>Janvier 1996  </DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="SCOPE_f"> Scicos visualization block  </SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <DESCRIPTION>
  <P>
    This block realizes the visualization of the evolution of the signals
    on the standard input port(s) at instants of events on the event
    input port.
  </P>
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <ITEMIZE label='DIALOGUE PARAMETERS'>
  <ITEM label='Curve colors'>
: a vector of integers. The i-th element is the color number (&gt;0) or dash type (&lt;0) used to draw the evolution of the i-th  input port signal. See <VERB>plot2d</VERB> for color (dash type) definitions.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Output window number'>
: The number of graphic window used for the display. It is often good to use high values to avoid conflict with palettes and Super Block windows. If you have more than one scope, make sure they don&apos;t have the same window numbers (unless superposition of the curves is desired).

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Output window position'>
: a 2 vector specifying the coordinates of the upper left corner of the graphic window. Answer [] for default window position.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Output window size'>
: a 2 vector specifying the width and height  of  the graphic window. Answer [] for default window dimensions.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Ymin, Ymax'>
: Minimum and maximum values of the input; used to set up the Y-axis of the plot in the graphics window.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Refresh period'>
: Maximum value on the X-axis (time). The plot is redrawn when time reaches a multiple of this value.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Buffer size'>
: To improve efficiency it is possible to buffer the input data. The drawing is only done after each <VERB>Buffer size</VERB> call to the block.

  </ITEM>
  <ITEM label='Accept herited events'>
: if 0 <VERB>SCOPE_f</VERB> draws a new point only when an event occurs on its event input port. if 1 <VERB>SCOPE_f</VERB> draws a new point when an event occurs on its event input port and when it&apos;s regular input changes due to an event on an other upstrem block (herited events). 

  </ITEM>
  </ITEMIZE>
  <ITEMIZE label='REMARKS'>
  <P>
    Output window number, Output window size, Output window position are only taken into account at the initialisation time of the simulation.  
  </P>
  </ITEMIZE>
  <SEE_ALSO>
    <SEE_ALSO_ITEM> <LINK>SCOPXY_f</LINK> </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>     <SEE_ALSO_ITEM> <LINK>EVENTSCOPE_f</LINK> </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>     <SEE_ALSO_ITEM> <LINK>ANIMXY_f</LINK> </SEE_ALSO_ITEM>
  </SEE_ALSO>
</MAN>
