<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Scicos
 * 
 * Copyright (C) INRIA - METALAU Project <scicos@inria.fr> (HTML version)
 * Copyright (C) DIGITEO - Scilab Consortium (XML Docbook version)
 * 
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
 * it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
 * the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
 *  (at your option) any later version.
 * 
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 * 
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
 * along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
 * Foundation, Inc., 675 Mass Ave, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA.
 * 
 * See the file ./license.txt
 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="Menu_entries">
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Menu_entries</refname>
    <refpurpose>Entrées des menus de l'éditeur</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsection id="Filemenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>File menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:New</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Clicking on the New menu item loads an empty diagram in the active editor Scicos window. If the previous content of the window is not saved, it will be lost. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Open</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Open menu item to load an ASCII or binary file containing a saved block diagram or palette. A dialog box allows user choosing the file. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Rename</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to change the diagram name. An editable dialog box opens. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Save (s)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the save menu item to save the block diagram in a binary file already selected by a previous select the Save As menu item. If you select this menu item and you have never clicked on the Save As menu item, the diagram is saved in the current directory as "window_name".cos where "window_name" is the name of the window appearing on top of the window (usually Untitled or Super Block).
The .cos binary files are machine independent.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Save As</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Save As menu item to save the block diagram or palette in a file. A dialog box allows choosing the file which must have a .cos or .cosf extension. The diagram takes the name of the file (without the extension).
If extension is ".cosf" an ASCII  formatted save is performed
       instead of binary save. Formatted save is slower than regular 
       save.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Save as Interf Func</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select "the Save as Interf. Func." menu item to save the diagram as a new Scicos block. A Scilab function is generated and saved in a file with ".sci" extension. File name and path are to be set in a "File menu" dialog. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Export</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu is used to export a figure of the current Scicos diagram. The export can be done directly in postscript format or done first in a graphic window to export in a second step in all the format that scilab can provide. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Export All</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu is used to export Scicos diagrams in postscript format. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Exit Scicos</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Click on the Exit Scicos menu item to close Scicos. That menu allows to return to Scilab session even if the current diagram is a Super block. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">File:Quit (q)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Click on the Quit menu item to close current diagram. If current diagram is not a Super block, Exit menu closes Scicos and returns to Scilab session. Save your diagram or/and your palette before leaving.
File/Close menu has the same effect.
  </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Diagrammenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>Diagram menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Diagram:Replot (r)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Replot menu item to replot the content of the graphics window. Graphics window stores complete history of the editing session in memory.
Replot is useful for 'cleaning' this memory.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Diagram:Purge</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Purge menu item to get a clean data structure. If diagram has been hugely modified many deleted blocks may remain in the data structure. It may be useful to suppress then before saving. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Diagram:Set Diagram Info</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to set user's diagram information. This info is stored in the diagram data structure and may be used for diagram documentation.
Information format may be redefined by user.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Diagram:Region to Super Block</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to transform a rectangular region of the current diagram by a super block. Click on a corner of the region, drag an click left to fix the region (left click cancels selection).
Region is replaced by a super block and links are redrawn.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Diagram:Up To Main Diagram</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Opens, if closed, and puts the focus on the main diagram. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Diagram:Context</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> When you select this menu item you obtain a dialog to enter Scilab instructions for defining symbolic Scicos parameters used in block definitions or to do whatever you want.
These instructions will be evaluated each time the diagram 
       is loaded.
 
If you change the value of a symbolic Scicos parameters in 
       the context, all the blocks are updated (Eval is performed).
  </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Palettemenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>Palette menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Palette:Palettes</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Palettes menu item to open a predefined palette. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Palette:Pal editor</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Pal editor allows you to define and reorder the list of palettes. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Palette:Load as Palette</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select this Load menu item to load an ASCII or binary file containing a saved block diagram as a palette. A dialog box allows user choosing the file. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Palette:Save as Palette</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Save as Palette menu item to save the block diagram as a palette in a file. A dialog box allows choosing the file which must have a .cos or .cosf extension. The palette takes the name of the file (without the extension).
If extension is ".cosf" an ASCII  formatted save is performed
       instead of binary save. It may take a while.
 
.scilab user file is updated if necessary.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Palette:Pal Tree</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> An alternative to Palettes menu for accessing palettes. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Editmenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>Edit menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Undo (u)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Undo menu item to undo the last edit operation. It is not possible to undo more!. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Cut</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Cut is used to remove the selected object from the diagram and keep a copy in the clipboard if the object is a block. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Copy</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Copy is used to place a copy of the selected object in the clipboard if the object is a block. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Paste</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Paste places the object in the Clipboard in the diagram. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Duplicate (c)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To duplicate a block in the active editor Scicos window select first the Duplicate menu item, then click (with left button) on the to-be-copied block in Scicos windows or in a palette), and finally click left where you want the copy be placed in the active editor Scicos window.
The lower left corner of the block is placed
       at the selected point.
 
Right click cancel the copy action.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Delete (d)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To delete blocks or a links, select first the Delete menu item, then click successively on the selected objects (with left button).
When you delete a block all links connected to it
       are deleted as well.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Move (m)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To move a block in the active editor Scicos window or in edited palette, select first the Move menu item, then click on the selected block, link segment or link corner, drag the mouse to the desired new block position and click left again to fix the position.
Right click cancel the move action.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Smart Move (z)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To move a block in the active editor Scicos window or in edited palette keeping horizontal and vertical links, select first the "Smart Move" menu item, then click on the selected block, link segment or link corner, drag the mouse to the desired new position and click left again to fix the position.
Right click cancel the move action.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Align (a)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To obtain nice diagrams, you can align ports of different blocks, vertically and horizontally. Select first the Align menu item, then click on the first port and finally on the second port. The block corresponding to the second port is moved.
A connected block cannot be aligned.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Flip (f)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To reverse the positions of the (regular) inputs and outputs of a block placed on its sides, select the Flip menu item first and then click on the selected block. This does not affect the order, nor the position of the input and output event ports which are numbered from left to right. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Rotate Left (t)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Rotate Left allows to turn a block on the Left. Each time the block is turned left, his angle is decresead of 45 degrees.
If no blocks or many blocks are selected, this is
       the block under the mouse pointer which turns.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Rotate Right (T)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Rotate Right allows to turn a block on the right. Each time the block is turned right, his angle is incresead of 45 degrees.
If no blocks or many blocks are selected, this is
       the block under the mouse pointer which turns.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Add new block</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To add a newly defined block to the current palette or diagram select first this menu item. A dialog box will pop up asking for the name of the GUI function associated with the block. If this function is not already loaded it was search in the current directory. The user may then click at the desired position of the block icon. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Block Documentation</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to set or get documentation for a block.
Selecting this menu and clicking on a block opens an
       editable dialog box.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Edit:Label</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To add a label to block, select first this menu item, click next on the desired block. A dialog appear that allows you to enter the desired label. Labels are used to import data from a block in an other one. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Viewmenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>View menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">View:Zoom in (+)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> When you select this menu item the diagram is zoomed in by a factor of 10%. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">View:Zoom out (-)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> When you select this menu item the diagram is zoomed out by a factor of 10%. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">View:Fit diagram to figure (=)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> When you select this menu item the diagram is fit to the size of the current window. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">View:Default window parameters</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">View:Available Parameters</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu shows the list of symbolic parameters defined in various contexts and available for use in the definition of block parameters in this diagram. The values of the parameters are also displayed (unless the size is too big. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">View:Grid (g)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Show/hide a grid in the current diagram. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Simulatemenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>Simulate menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Simulate:Setup</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> In the main Scicos window, clicking on the Setup menu item invokes a dialog box that allows you to change integration parameters:
- Final integration time (integration ends at
                 this time, it always starts from 0), 
 
- Real time scaling (forces real time simulation
                 by setting Scicos unit of time to 1 second), 
 
- Absolute and relative error tolerances (solver properties), 
 
- Time tolerance (the smallest time interval for which 
               the ode solver is used to update continuous states), 
 
- Max integration time interval (the maximum time interval
           for each call to solver, it must be reduced if the error
           message "too many calls" is encountered), 
 
- Solver (choose the numerical solver to be used), 
 
Max step size (max time step taken by solver).
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Simulate:Compile</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Compile menu item to compile the block diagram. This menu item need never be used since compilation is performed automatically, if necessary, before the beginning of every simulation (Run menu item).
Normally, a new compilation is not needed if only
       system parameters and internal states are modified.
       In some cases however these modifications are not
       correctly updated and a manual compilation may be
       needed before a Restart or a Continue.
       Please report if you encounter such a case.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Simulate:Eval</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> All dialogs user answers may be Scilab instructions. They are evaluated immediately and stored as character strings. Select this menu item to have them re-evaluated according to new values of underlying Scilab variables.
These underlying Scilab variables may be user global variables
       defined before Scicos was launch, They may also be defined in
       by the Scicos context (see Context menu item).
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Simulate:Debug Level</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Set the debug level: 0 (no debugging), 1 (light debugging information printout), 2 (more information printout and execution of Debug Block if any in diagram), 3 (silent debugging mode). </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Simulate:Run</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Select the Run menu item to start the simulation. If the system has already been simulated, a dialog box appears where you can choose to Continue, Restart or End the simulation.
You may interrupt the simulation by clicking on the 
       "stop" button, change any of the block parameters
       and continue the simulation with the new values.
  </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Formatmenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>Format menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Set grid</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Set the size and the color of the grid for the current diagram. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Add color</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to add new color to the diagram private color map. Added colors are stored in the diagram data structure. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Default link colors</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to change the default color for regular and activation links. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Color</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To change the background color of an object, select first this menu item, click next on the desired object. A dialog appear that allows you to choose the desired color. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Background color</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to change the background and default foreground colors. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Show Block Shadow</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to select 3D shape for blocks and associated parameters. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Resize</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To change the size of a block, select first this menu item, click next on the desired block. A dialog appear that allows you to change the width and/or height of the block shape. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Identification</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to set an identificator to a link or a block block identificators are drawn under the block icon. Super blocks input/output ports identificators are replicated over the block shape ports. Links identificators are not displayed.
Selecting this menu and clicking on a block or links opens an
       editable dialog box.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:ID fonts</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to change the font used to write in the block identifications (see "Set block ID" menu). </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Icon</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To change the icon of a block, select first this menu item, click next on the desired block. A dialog appear that allows you to enter Scilab instructions used to draw the icon.
You may use the icon_editor menu to generate the Scilab
       instructions.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Format:Icon Editor</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Icon Editor allows you to define graphically the icon of the block. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="Toolsmenu_Menu_entries">
    <title>Tools menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Create Mask</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu applies only to a Super Block, transforming it into a block that resembles a basic block with a standard dialog box. The block parameters are identifed automatically by searching all the symbolic parameters used in the definition of the block parameters inside the Super block that are not defined in the appropriate contexts within the Super Block; </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Remove Mask</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu applies only to an already masked block. It removes the mask and the Super Block within it can be recovered. Note that the icon of the Super Block remains the same as that of the masked block. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Customize Mask</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Creating a mask leads to a block with parameters that can be set by the block's dialog box. The title and the description of the parameters in the dialog box can be set by this menu. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Save Block GUI</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This operation can only be applied to a masked block (see Create Mask operation). The result, the interfacing function of this block, is saved in an .sci file, which can be placed in any diagram/palette using the Add New Block operation. The interfacing function is loaded autmatically for immediate use after the operation.
Note that the resulting block is not a masked block; it is a compiled super block.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Get Info (i)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows user to obtain information on an object and on its connection with other diagram objects.
Select this menu and click on an object. See also 'Details' menu.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Details</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This item can be applied to a block, link or text. It can also be applied to the diagram. In either case, it displays the content of the Scilab structure defining the object. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Browser</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu opens a graphic window with a tree representation of the super blocks hierarchy. Each node represents a Super Block.
Browser window is useful to open directly a Super Block
       everywhere in the hierarchy. To open the main diagram if it has
       been closed, use the 'Up to Main Diagram' menu.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Code Generation</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This menu allows to generate the simulation code associated with a discrete time Super Block.
The code generation is obtained simply by selecting this menu and  
       then the desired Super Block.
 
If the Super Block satisfies the required conditions, a dialog box
       pops up to ask for a block name, a directory where to put the
       generated files and for optional libraries requested by the linker.
 
Given this information the code is generated, compiled and linked with 
       Scilab. The Super Block is automatically replaced by a new block which 
       implements the generated code. It is then possible to run the modified 
       diagram. The code for standalone use is also generated.
  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Shortcuts</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> Used to define personalized shortcuts. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Activate Scilab Window</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> This item activates the Scilab window without closing the Scicos diagram. You can use Scilab as usual and later return to editing your Scicos diagram. Note that if you activate the Scilab window with this menu without saving your diagram, if you leave Scilab without returning to Scicos, your diagram will be lost. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tools:Calc</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> When you select this menu item you switch Scilab to the pause mode (see the help on pause). In the Scilab main window and you may enter Scilab instructions as usual. In most cases, user should use the 'Activate Scilab Window' menu instead. The 'Calc' menu should only be used for advanced debugging. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
  <refsection id="menu_Menu_entries">
    <title>? menu</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">?:Help (h)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> To get help on an object or menu buttons, select first Help menu item and then on the selected object or menu item. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">?:Scicos Documentation</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> That item opens the html browser. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">?:Demos</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> The Demos menu allows to open some examples of scicos diagram. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">?:About Scicos</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para> About Scicos item display the current version of Scicos and gives some useful informations. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
