<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Scilab ( http://www.scilab.org/ ) - This file is part of Scilab
 * Copyright (C) 2006 - INRIA - Allan CORNET
 *
 * Copyright (C) 2012 - 2016 - Scilab Enterprises
 *
 * This file is hereby licensed under the terms of the GNU GPL v2.0,
 * pursuant to article 5.3.4 of the CeCILL v.2.1.
 * This file was originally licensed under the terms of the CeCILL v2.1,
 * and continues to be available under such terms.
 * For more information, see the COPYING file which you should have received
 * along with this program.
 *
 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:lang="en" xml:id="TCL_EvalFile">
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>TCL_EvalFile</refname>
        <refpurpose>Reads and evaluate a tcl/tk
            file
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
        <title>Syntax</title>
        <synopsis>TCL_EvalFile(filename [,interp])</synopsis>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsection>
        <title>Arguments</title>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>filename</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>character string. Contains the name of the file to read and
                        evaluate.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>interp</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>optional character string parameter. Name of the slave tcl
                        interpreter in which the operation has to be performed. If not
                        provided, it defaults to the main tcl interpreter created by
                        Scilab.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>With this routine, one can read and evaluate the content of a file
            containing tcl/tk scripts. This allows to create powerful tk
            interfaces.
        </para>
        <para>The filename might be relative or absolute.</para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Advantages and drawbacks of this functionality</title>
        <para>This routines allows to use directly tcl/tk scripts. This thus allows,
            for instance to use Interface Builders such as SpecTcl to design the
            interface. The interfaces built directly with tcl/tk scripts are much
            faster than the ones built with the Scilab Graphic Object library provided
            with tksci (see uicontrol for example). Indeed, those Objects are wrappers
            around tk graphic widgets. Nevertheless, this way of creating graphic user
            interface should only be used when one aims at addressing directly
            specific tk/tcl features. There are two main reasons for this. First of
            all, there is no simple way to manipulate Scilab objects from within a
            tcl/tk script. Thus, the interface designer has to write two sets of
            callbacks routines. One to describe the changes occuring in the interface
            when the user acts on the widgets. The second set of call routines will
            perform the (pure) Scilab reactions to the user actions.
        </para>
        <para>Here is an example: Suppose you design a scrollbar corresponding to a
            spline tension value. You want the spline to be displayed in a graphic
            windows and updated each time the user moves the scrollbar. At the same
            time, you want the value of this tension parameter to be displayed within
            the Interface. You will have to write a first tcl/tk (callback) function
            which will be automatically called by the tk scrollbar ("-command"
            option). This callback function will update the displayed value of the
            parameter in the interface and will then call the scilab routine
            ("ScilabEval" command) to update the graph.
        </para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Remarks on the tcl/tk script style</title>
        <para>Because Scilab manages the tcl/tk events, it creates the root window
            ".", this window should not be destroyed nor directly used by your tcl/tk
            scripts. You should thus always create your own toplevel windows.
            Moreover, since this module was written at a time when namespaces didn't
            exist, some variables defined by scilab tcl/tk scripts could collide your
            code. Running your scripts in a slave interpreter may help in such a
            case.
        </para>
        <para>
            More information about Tcl/Tk: <ulink url="http://www.tcl.tk/doc/">http://www.tcl.tk/doc/</ulink>
        </para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Examples</title>
        <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[
TCL_EvalFile(SCI+"/modules/tclsci/demos/tk/puzzle");
 ]]></programlisting>
    </refsection>
    <refsection role="see also">
        <title>See also</title>
        <simplelist type="inline">
            <member>
                <link linkend="ScilabEval">ScilabEval</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="TCL_EvalStr">TCL_EvalStr</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="TCL_GetVar">TCL_GetVar</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="TCL_SetVar">TCL_SetVar</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="TCL_ExistVar">TCL_ExistVar</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="TCL_UnsetVar">TCL_UnsetVar</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="TCL_UpVar">TCL_UpVar</link>
            </member>
        </simplelist>
    </refsection>
</refentry>
