<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 * Scilab ( http://www.scilab.org/ ) - This file is part of Scilab
 * Copyright (C) 2013 - Scilab Enterprises - Adeline CARNIS
 *
 * Copyright (C) 2012 - 2016 - Scilab Enterprises
 *
 * This file is hereby licensed under the terms of the GNU GPL v2.0,
 * pursuant to article 5.3.4 of the CeCILL v.2.1.
 * This file was originally licensed under the terms of the CeCILL v2.1,
 * and continues to be available under such terms.
 * For more information, see the COPYING file which you should have received
 * along with this program.
 *
 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:id="optimsimplex_overview" xml:lang="en">
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>overview</refname>
        <refpurpose>An overview of the Optimsimplex toolbox.</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <para>
            The goal of this component is to provide a building block for optimization algorithms
            based on a simplex. The optimsimplex package may be used in the following
            optimization methods:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>the Spendley et al. simplex method,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the Nelder-Mead method,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the Box algorithm for constrained optimization,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the multi-dimensional search by Virginia Torczon,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>etc...</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            This toolboxes is designed with Oriented Object ideas in mind.
        </para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Features</title>
        <para>
            The following is a list of features the Nelder-Mead prototype algorithm currently
            provides:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Manage various simplex initializations</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>initial simplex given by user,</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            initial simplex computed with a length and along the
                            coordinate axes,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            initial regular simplex computed with Spendley et al.
                            formula,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            initial simplex computed by a small perturbation around the
                            initial guess point,
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>initial simplex computed from randomized bounds.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Sort the vertices by increasing function values,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Compute the standard deviation of the function values in the simplex, </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Compute the simplex gradient with forward or centered differences, </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Shrink the simplex toward the best vertex. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>
            This set of commands allows to manage a simplex made of k&gt;=n+1
            points in a n-dimensional space. This component is the building block for
            a class of direct search optimization methods such as the Nelder-Mead
            algorithm or Torczon's Multi-Dimensional Search.
        </para>
        <para>
            A simplex is designed as a collection of k&gt;=n+1 vertices. Each
            vertex is made of a point and a function value at that point.
        </para>
        <para>
            The simplex can be created with various shapes. It can be configured
            and queried at will. The simplex can also be reflected or shrinked. The
            simplex gradient can be computed with an order 1 forward formula and with an
            order 2 centered formula.
        </para>
        <para>
            The optimsimplex_new function allows to create a simplex. If
            vertices coordinates are given, there are registered in the simplex. If a
            function is provided, it is evaluated at each vertex. The
            optimsimplex_destroy function destroys the object and frees internal
            memory. Several functions allow to create a simplex with special shapes,
            including axes-by-axes (optimsimplex_axes), regular
            (optimsimplex_spendley), randomized bounds simplex with arbitrary nbve
            vertices (optimsimplex_randbounds) and a heuristical small variation
            around a given point (optimsimplex_pfeffer).
        </para>
        <para>
            In the following functions, simplices and vertices are, depending on
            the functions either input or output arguments. The following general
            principle have been used to manage the storing of the coordinates of the
            points.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The vertices are stored row by row, while the coordinates are
                    stored column by column. This implies the following rules.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The coordinates of a vertex are stored in a row vector, i.e. a 1
                    x n matrix where n is the dimension of the space.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The function values are stored in a column vector, i.e. a nbve x
                    1 matrix where nbve is the number of vertices.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Example : Creating a simplex with randomized bounds</title>
        <para>
            In the following example, one creates a simplex with in the 2D
            domain [-5 5]^2, with [-1.2 1.0] as the first vertex. One uses the
            randomized bounds method to generate a simplex with 5 vertices. The
            function takes an additional argument mystuff, which is counts the number
            of times the function is called. After the creation of the simplex, the
            value of mystuff.nb is 5, which is the expected result because there is
            one function call by vertex.
        </para>
        <programlisting role="example"><![CDATA[
function y = rosenbrock (x)
  y = 100*(x(2)-x(1)^2)^2+(1-x(1))^2;
endfunction
function [ y , mystuff ] = mycostf ( x , mystuff )
  y = rosenbrock(x);
  mystuff.nb = mystuff.nb + 1
endfunction

mystuff = tlist(["T_MYSTUFF","nb"]);
mystuff.nb = 0;
[ s1 , mystuff ] = optimsimplex_new ( "randbounds" , [-1.2 1.0], mycostf, ...
  [-5.0 -5.0] , [5.0 5.0], 5 , mystuff );
s1
mprintf("Function evaluations: %d\n",mystuff.nb)
s1 = optimsimplex_destroy ( s1 );
]]></programlisting>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Initial simplex strategies</title>
        <para>
            In this section, we analyse the various initial simplex which are
            provided in this component.
        </para>
        <para>
            It is known that direct search methods based on simplex designs are
            very sensitive to the initial simplex. This is why the current component
            provides various ways to create such an initial simplex.
        </para>
        <para>
            The first historical simplex-based algorithm is the one presented in
            "Sequential Application of Simplex Designs in Optimisation and
            Evolutionary Operation" by W. Spendley, G. R. Hext and F. R. Himsworth.
            The "spendley" simplex creates the regular simplex which is
            presented in the paper.
        </para>
        <para>
            The "randbounds" simplex is due to
            M.J. Box in "A New Method of Constrained Optimization and a Comparison
            With Other Methods".
        </para>
        <para>
            Pfeffer's method is a heuristic which is presented in "Global
            Optimization Of Lennard-Jones Atomic Clusters" by Ellen Fan. It is due to
            L. Pfeffer at Stanford and it is used in fminsearch.
        </para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection>
        <title>Bibliography</title>
        <para>
            &#8220;Sequential Application of Simplex Designs in Optimisation and
            Evolutionary Operation&#8221;, Spendley, W. and Hext, G. R. and Himsworth,
            F. R., American Statistical Association and American Society for Quality,
            1962
        </para>
        <para>
            "A Simplex Method for Function Minimization", Nelder, J. A. and
            Mead, R. The Computer Journal, January, 1965, 308--313
        </para>
        <para>
            "A New Method of Constrained Optimization and a Comparison With
            Other Methods", M. J. Box, The Computer Journal 1965 8(1):42-52, 1965 by
            British Computer Society
        </para>
        <para>
            "Iterative Methods for Optimization", C.T. Kelley, 1999, Chapter 6.,
            section 6.2
        </para>
        <para>
            "Compact Numerical Methods For Computers - Linear Algebra and
            Function Minimization", J.C. Nash, 1990, Chapter 14. Direct Search
            Methods
        </para>
        <para>
            "Sequential Application of Simplex Designs in Optimisation and
            Evolutionary Operation", W. Spendley, G. R. Hext, F. R. Himsworth,
            Technometrics, Vol. 4, No. 4 (Nov., 1962), pp. 441-461, Section 3.1
        </para>
        <para>
            "A New Method of Constrained Optimization and a Comparison With
            Other Methods", M. J. Box, The Computer Journal 1965 8(1):42-52, 1965 by
            British Computer Society
        </para>
        <para>
            &#8220;Detection and Remediation of Stagnation in the Nelder--Mead
            Algorithm Using a Sufficient Decrease Condition&#8221;, SIAM J. on
            Optimization, Kelley,, C. T., 1999
        </para>
        <para>
            " Multi-Directional Search: A Direct Search Algorithm for Parallel
            Machines", by E. Boyd, Kenneth W. Kennedy, Richard A. Tapia, Virginia
            Joanne Torczon,, Virginia Joanne Torczon, 1989, Phd Thesis, Rice
            University
        </para>
        <para>
            "Grid Restrained Nelder-Mead Algorithm", Árpád B&#361;rmen, Janez
            Puhan, Tadej Tuma, Computational Optimization and Applications, Volume 34
            , Issue 3 (July 2006), Pages: 359 - 375
        </para>
        <para>
            "A convergent variant of the Nelder-Mead algorithm", C. J. Price, I.
            D. Coope, D. Byatt, Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications,
            Volume 113 , Issue 1 (April 2002), Pages: 5 - 19,
        </para>
        <para>
            "Global Optimization Of Lennard-Jones Atomic Clusters", Ellen Fan,
            Thesis, February 26, 2002, McMaster University
        </para>
    </refsection>
</refentry>
