<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../manrev.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>scipad</TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scilab Function</TYPE>
  <DATE>31-May-2004</DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="scipad"> Embedded Scilab text editor</SHORT_DESCRIPTION>
  <CALLING_SEQUENCE>
    <CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>scipad() </CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>
    <CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>scipad(f) </CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>
    <CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>scipad([f1,f2,...]) </CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>
    <CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>scipad f1 f2 ... </CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>
   </CALLING_SEQUENCE>
  <PARAM>
    <PARAM_INDENT>
      <PARAM_ITEM>
        <PARAM_NAME>f, f1, f2...</PARAM_NAME>
        <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
          <SP>: file pathnames</SP>
        </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
      </PARAM_ITEM>
   </PARAM_INDENT>
  </PARAM>
  <DESCRIPTION>
  <P>
   Scipad is an embedded Scilab text editor written in TCL/TK. 
   It can be started with the &quot;Editor&quot; 
   button on top of the main Scilab window, or from Scilab command line 
   with the instruction <VERB>scipad()</VERB> 
   or <VERB>scipad f</VERB>. 
  </P>
  <P>
   The same invocation adds further files to an already opened scipad session.
   Scipad allows Windows like edition modes. Keyboard shortcuts are defined for most possible 
   editing actions and reported by the menu entries.
  </P>
  <P>
   Additionally, the following shortcuts are defined:
  </P>
    <ITEMIZE label="shortcuts">
      <ITEM label="&lt;F2&gt;">
        <SP> Save file </SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;F5&gt;">
        <SP> Save file and run it into Scilab</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;F6&gt;, &lt;Control-F6&gt;">
        <SP> show next buffer</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;F7&gt;, &lt;Control-F7&gt;">
        <SP> show previous buffer</SP>
      </ITEM>      <ITEM label="&lt;double-click mouse-button1&gt;">
        <SP> Select word</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;triple-click mouse-button1&gt;">
        <SP> Select line</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;mouse-button2&gt;">
        <SP> Paste selection (unix)</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;mouse-button3&gt;">
        <SP> popup edit menu</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;Shift-mouse-button3&gt;">
        <SP> popup Execute menu</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;Control-mouse-button3&gt;">
        <SP> popup Options menu</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;Control-plus&gt;">
        <SP> increase the font size</SP>
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM label="&lt;Control-minus&gt;">
        <SP> decrease the font size</SP>
      </ITEM>
     </ITEMIZE>
  <P>
      The &quot;Load Into Scilab&quot; (Ctrl-lowercase-l) menu entry can be used to
      <LINK>exec</LINK> the file contents into Scilab, while &quot;Execute selection&quot; (Ctrl-lowercase-y)
      passes the selected lines to the scilab shell using <LINK>ScilabEval</LINK>
      (i.e. <LINK>execstr</LINK>).
  </P>
  <P>
  </P>
  </DESCRIPTION>

  <SECTION label="Debugger">
    <P>Scipad 2.0 and later includes a debugger (for .sci files only). 
    The user can:</P>
  <ITEMIZE>

     <ITEM label="1. Set/remove breakpoints anywhere in the buffer"><SP>.
       This is just text tags management (nice pink background, etc.).</SP> 
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="2. Configure execution"><SP>.
       The user has to provide the function name to  
       execute, its variable names, and variable values. To ease this step, 
       a scan of the currently displayed buffer is implemented to look for
       functions defined in it, scan their names and variable names.
       All this is displayed to the user in a dialog for     
       easy selection. First, he has to select a function in a spinbox (sorry, 
       but comboboxes are not available natively in tk), then eventually one
       of its variables (in a listbox). Once a variable is selected, the user can
       set/change its value (another dialog pops). Variable values and names
       are displayed in listboxes. The user can also add or remove a new
       variable. This is in case the user changes the input variables of his
       function in the file, and he does not want to scan the buffer again
       (which causes all the variable values to reset to "").</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="3. Launch execution with breakpoints"><SP>.
       Scipad execs the <VERB>current</VERB> buffer to
       Scilab, sends to Scilab the <LINK>setbpt</LINK> instructions relative to the
       <VERB>function selected at step 2</VERB> (which may be different from the one he
       sees in the displayed buffer), and executes the selected function with
       the provided input variable values. Then the execution is automagically
       stopped by Scilab at the first breakpoint.</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4"><SP>. Now there are several possibilities for the user:</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4.1. Continue up to next breakpoint"><SP>.
       Just a <LINK>resume</LINK> sent to Scilab, and an update of the active breakpoint display.
       The active breakpoint is underlined in Scipad.</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4.2. Insert/Remove a new breakpoint during the debug"><SP>.
       Scipad sends a <LINK>setbpt</LINK> (or <LINK>delbpt</LINK>).</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4.3. Step by step execution"><SP>.
       This is what I'm currently fighting at (it
       is disabled in the Debug menu for the time being).
       See proc stepbystep_bp in SCI/tcl/scipadsources/debugger.tcl for further details about the problems I
       encounter.</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4.4. Continue ignoring any breakpoint"><SP>. Finish 
       execution as if there
       was no breakpoint: Breakpoints are removed from Scilab but kept in Scipad.
       Scipad sends adequate <LINK>delbpt</LINK>, 
       then <LINK>resume</LINK>.</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4.5. Display call stack"><SP>. Scipad sends a <LINK>whereami</LINK> 
       to Scilab. Sometimes useful.</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="4.6. Abort debug"><SP>: Scipad sends adequate <LINK>delbpt</LINK>, 
       then sends <LINK>abort</LINK> to Scilab.</SP>
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM label="5. Remove all breakpoints"><SP>. This is a command to remove 
       all the breakpoints in Scilab, in case something did not run as expected.
       Currently, this may be useful in case of loss of first characters sent
       by <LINK>ScilabEval</LINK>, which still may occur, and which produce errors in the
       Scilab shell.</SP>
       </ITEM>
    </ITEMIZE>

  <P>
    Of course, after the end of the execution, the breakpoints are removed 
    from Scilab (but kept in Scipad). All this can be invoked through a nice debug menu,
    with adequate accelerators and shortcuts.
    All what I have just described above works well with functions, i.e. ..sci  files.
    I thought about .sce files, but <LINK>setbpt</LINK> essentially cannot be used with them.
    However, the .sce case is foreseen in all the procs of SCI/tcl/scipadsources/debugger.tcl.
    That means that a .sce file will not crash scipad, which is  the very least, but more, 
    once I figure out a solution it should be easy to add the functionality.
    Anyway, if actually a debug is required in a .sce, the user could first turn it
    into a .sci function adding (output_vars)=function foo(input_vars) and that's it.  
    The absence of breakpoints management for .sce is therefore not such a  major disadvantage.
  </P>
  <P>
  </P>
  </SECTION>

  <SECTION label="Remarks">
  <ITEMIZE>
  <ITEM label="Known Issues:">
      <ITEMIZE>
      <ITEM label="Execute Selection">
         <SP> deals only with selections containing less than 16000 characters.
          It gets confused if the selection contains a 
         <VERB>function</VERB> 
          not terminated by an <VERB>endfunction</VERB>. The commands passed are output on the Scilab
          window, but are not recorded in the history. </SP>
      </ITEM>
      </ITEMIZE>
   </ITEM>
  <ITEM label="Bugs:"> <SP> There are still a few... </SP>
  </ITEM>
  </ITEMIZE>
  </SECTION>


  <EXAMPLE>
<![CDATA[ 
   scipad SCI/scilab.star 
]]>
  </EXAMPLE>

  <AUTHORS>
  <AUTHORS_ITEM>
    Scipad is derived from <VERB>tknotepad</VERB> written by Joseph Acosta;
  </AUTHORS_ITEM>
  <AUTHORS_ITEM>
   Mathieu Philippe, INRIA, 2001;
  </AUTHORS_ITEM>
  <AUTHORS_ITEM>
   Enrico Segre, Weizmann Institute, 2003-2004;
  </AUTHORS_ITEM>
  <AUTHORS_ITEM>
   Francois Vogel, 2004.
  </AUTHORS_ITEM>
  </AUTHORS>
</MAN>