<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MAN SYSTEM "../../manrev.dtd">
<MAN>
  <LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE>
  <TITLE>pca</TITLE>
  <TYPE>Scilab Function  </TYPE>
  <DATE>19-Sep-2003</DATE>
  <SHORT_DESCRIPTION name="pca">  Principal components analysis</SHORT_DESCRIPTION>

  <CALLING_SEQUENCE>
  <CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>[lambda,facpr,comprinc] = pca(x,N)</CALLING_SEQUENCE_ITEM>
  </CALLING_SEQUENCE>

  <PARAM>
  <PARAM_INDENT>

    <PARAM_ITEM>
    <PARAM_NAME>x</PARAM_NAME>
    <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
       <SP>:  is a nxp (n  individuals, p variables) real matrix</SP>

    </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
    </PARAM_ITEM>

    <PARAM_ITEM>
    <PARAM_NAME>N</PARAM_NAME>
    <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>

      <SP> : is a 2x1 integer vector. Its coefficients point to
         the eigenvectors  corresponding to the  eigenvalues
         of the correlation  matrix pxp  ordered by  decreasing
         values of eigenvalues.  If  N is  missing, we suppose
         N=[1 2].</SP>

    </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
    </PARAM_ITEM>

    <PARAM_ITEM>
    <PARAM_NAME>lambda</PARAM_NAME>
    <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
       <SP>: is  a px2  numerical  matrix.  In the  first
         column we  find the eigenvalues of  V, where V
         is the correlation pxp matrix and in the second
         column are the ratios of the corresponding 
         eigenvalue over the sum of eigenvalues.</SP>

    </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
    </PARAM_ITEM>

    <PARAM_ITEM>
    <PARAM_NAME>facpr</PARAM_NAME>
    <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
      <SP> : are the  principal  factors: eigenvectors  of
         V. Each column is an eigenvector element of the
         dual of R^p.</SP>

    </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
    </PARAM_ITEM>

    <PARAM_ITEM>
    <PARAM_NAME>comprinc</PARAM_NAME>
    <PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
       <SP>: are the  principal components.  Each column
         (c_i=Xu_i)  of   this  nxn  matrix   is  the
         M-orthogonal projection of  individuals onto
         principal  axis.  Each one of this  columns
         is a linear combination  of the variables
         x1,   ...,xp  with   maximum   variance  under
         condition u'_iM^(-1)u_i=1</SP>
    </PARAM_DESCRIPTION>
    </PARAM_ITEM>
  </PARAM_INDENT>
  </PARAM>
 
  <DESCRIPTION>
<P>
   This  function  performs  several  computations  known  as
   "principal  component analysis".  It  includes drawing  of
"correlations  circle", i.e.  in the  horizontal  axis the
correlation   values   r(c1;xj)   and  in   the   vertical
r(c2;xj). It is an extension of the pca function.
</P>
<P>
The  idea  behind this  method  is  to  represent in  an
approximative  manner a  cluster of  n individuals  in a
smaller  dimensional subspace.  In order  to do  that, it
projects the cluster onto a subspace.  The choice of the
k-dimensional projection subspace is  made in such a way
that  the distances  in  the projection  have a  minimal
deformation: we are looking for a k-dimensional subspace
such that the squares of the distances in the projection
is  as  big  as  possible  (in  fact  in  a  projection,
distances can only stretch).  In other words, inertia of
the projection  onto the k dimensional  subspace must be
maximal.
</P>
  </DESCRIPTION>

  <AUTHOR>
    Carlos Klimann
  </AUTHOR>

  <BIBLIO>
    <P>Saporta, Gilbert, Probabilites,  Analyse des
Donnees et Statistique, Editions Technip, Paris, 1990.</P>
  </BIBLIO>


</MAN>
