<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 * Scilab ( http://www.scilab.org/ ) - This file is part of Scilab
 * Copyright (C) 2006-2008 - INRIA
 *
 * This file must be used under the terms of the CeCILL.
 * This source file is licensed as described in the file COPYING, which
 * you should have received as part of this distribution.  The terms
 * are also available at
 * http://www.cecill.info/licences/Licence_CeCILL_V2-en.txt
 *
 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org" xml:lang="en" scilab:needs-examples="no" xml:id="intersci">
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>intersci</refname>
        <refpurpose>Scilab tool to interface C or Fortran functions with scilab. Deprecated: Please use SWIG</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsection>
        <title>Description</title>
        <para>
            All scilab primitive functions are defined in a set of interface
            routines. For each function the interfacing code checks first number of
            rhs and lhs arguments. Then it get pointers on input arguments in the
            Scilab data base and checks their types. After that it calls procedure
            associated with Scilab functions, checks returned errors flags and set
            the results in the data base.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal>intersci</literal> is a program which permits to interface automatically FORTRAN
            subroutines or C functions to Scilab
        </para>
        <para>
            With <literal>intersci</literal>, a user can group all his FORTRAN or C code into a same set,
            called an interface, and use them in Scilab as Scilab functions. The interfacing
            is made by creating a FORTRAN subroutine which has to be linked to
            Scilab  together
            with the user code. This complex FORTRAN subroutine is automatically generated
            by <literal>intersci</literal> from a description file of the interface.
        </para>
        <para>Refer to intersci documentation for more details.</para>
        <para>Note that this feature is obsolete and unsupported and will be replaced by a Scilab SWIG wrapper in an upcoming version.</para>
    </refsection>
    <refsection role="see also">
        <title>See Also</title>
        <simplelist type="inline">
            <member>
                <link linkend="fort">fort</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="external">external</link>
            </member>
            <member>
                <link linkend="addinter">addinter</link>
            </member>
        </simplelist>
    </refsection>
</refentry>
